Guide to the Stanford Institute for International Studies Records
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Stanford Institute for International Studies records
1978-2001
SC0559
Lyman, Richard W., 1923-2012.
Stanford Institute for International Studies.
8.5 Linear feet (13 boxes)
These records consist of two series: Richard W. Lyman's records as director of IIS and records from the affiliated research center, Asia/Pacific Research Center (A/PARC), some of which predate the creation of the IIS. Lyman's papers, 1988-1991, consist largely of his correspondence and texts of his speeches and talks. There is also a set of VHS tapes from the first annual meeting of the Advisory Council, 1991. Records from A/PARC, 1978-1995, pertain to the U.S.-Japan Legislators' Conferences, the Asia-Pacific Roundtable, and A/PARC's corporate affiliates; included are correspondence, memoranda, notes, reports, and meeting records.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
The collection was given to the Stanford University Archives as a gift from Richard W. Lyman in 1996, 2001, and 2003. Additional materials were received via administrative transfer in1999.
Information about Access
This collection is open for research; materials must be requested at least 48 hours in advance of intended use.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
Stanford University President Emeritus Richard W. Lyman founded the Institute for International Studies in 1988 and was its director until August 1991. The Institute brings experts from a variety of disciplines within the university together with long- and short-term visitors from other academic, government, and corporate institutions to study contemporary policy issues. Research is focused primarily on international security, the global environment, and international political economy. Research programs include the Northeast Asia-United States Forum on International Policy, the Center for International Security and Arms Control, the Americas Program, the Asia/Pacific Research Center, and the Stanford Japan Center-Research, located in Kyoto. The institute also oversees teaching programs and five area centers for African, East Asian, European, Latin American, and Russian and East European studies.
Description of the Collection
The records include Richard W. Lyman's records as director of IIS and records from the affiliated research center, Asia/Pacific Research Center (A/PARC), some of which predate the creation of the IIS. Lyman's papers, 1988-1991, consist largely of his correspondence and texts of his speeches and talks. There is also a set of VHS tapes from the first annual meeting of the Advisory Council, 1991. Records from A/PARC, 1978-1995, pertain to the U.S.-Japan Legislators' Conferences, the Asia-Pacific Roundtable, and A/PARC's corporate affiliates; included are correspondence, memoranda, notes, reports, and meeting records.
An additional accesion received in 2003 contains publications as well as video footage from the Advisory Council of the IIS First Annual Meeting, held January 24-25, 1991.
Access Terms
Lyman, Richard W., 1923-2012.; Stanford Institute for International Studies.; Stanford University. Institute for International Studies. Asia/Pacific Research Center.; East Asia--Foreign relations--United States; International relations.; United States--Foreign relations--East Asia
Collection Contents
- Richard W. Lyman Director's Records, Accession ARCH-1996-089
  - Chron file, 1988 Aug (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Chron file, 1988 Sep (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Chron file, 1988 Oct (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Chron file, 1988 Nov (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Chron file, 1988 Dec (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Chron file, 1989 Jan (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Chron file, 1989 Feb (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Chron file, 1989 Mar (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Chron file, 1989 Apr (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Chron file, 1989 May (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Chron file, 1989 Jun (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Chron file, 1989 Jul (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Chron file, 1989 Aug (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Chron file, 1989 Sep (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Chron file, 1989 Oct (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Chron file, 1989 Nov (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Chron file, 1989 Dec (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Chron file, 1990 Jan (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Chron file, 1990 Feb (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Chron file, 1990 Mar (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Chron file, 1990 Apr (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Chron file, 1990 May (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Chron file, 1990 Jun (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Chron file, 1990 Jul (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Chron file, 1990 Aug (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Chron file, 1990 Sep (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Chron file, 1990 Oct (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Chron file, 1990 Nov-Dec (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Chron file, 1991 Jan (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Chron file, 1991 Feb (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Chron file, 1991 Mar (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Chron file, 1991 Apr (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Chron file, 1991 May (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Chron file, 1991 Jun-Aug (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Centennial Convocation, 1991 Sep (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Fallen Leaf Lake, 1991 Aug (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Humboldt University (Germany) [three files in one], 1991 Jul (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Library Council talk, 1991 May (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Introduction: Pres. Perez, 1991 May (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Wesson lecture introduction, 1991 May (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Intercultural Resources Forum, Santa Clara, 1991 Apr (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Lane Lecture, 1991 Mar (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - British Studies Conference, 1991 Mar (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Founder's Day, 1991 Mar (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Swiss symposium, 1991 Mar (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Los Altos Morning Forum, 1991 Jan (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - East Bay development event, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Lyman award, 1990 Nov (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Bechtel talk (Globalization of Careers), 1990 Nov (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - IIS event (Warren Christopher luncheon in L.A.), 1990 Nov (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Ohio Wesleyan, 1990 Oct (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Independent Sector, tenth anniversary talk, 1990 Oct (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - "How New a World?" UNA, Gunn High School, 1990 June (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Stanford Alumni Centennial, 1990 May (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Bertelsmann Foundation, Germany, 1990 May (Box 5, Folder 1-4)
  - Germany, 1990 May (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Introduction of George Shultz, 1990 Mar (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Palo Alto Seniors, 1990 Mar (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Toronto, 1990 Mar (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - National Endowment for the Humanities (testimony), 1990 May (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Library Vis. Committee, 1990 Apr (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Boston, 1990 Mar (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - University seminar, 1990 Feb (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Friday Noon Live, 1989 Oct (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - JAPCU, 1989 Oct (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - CHART dinner, San Francisco, 1989 Sep (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Summer alumni, 1989 Aug (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Stanford alumni, Los Angeles, 1989 May (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - College of Idaho, Commencement speech, 1989 May (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Speech: Structures and Pacific Rim, 1989 May (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Knickerbocker Club, 1989 Apr (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Hoover Tower talks, 1989 Apr (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Bechtel speech, 1989 Mar (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Development, 1989 Feb (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Kampelman/Dubinin, 1989 Feb (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Columbus talk, 1989 Feb (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Monterey World Affairs Council, 1989 Jan (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Americas, 1988 Dec (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Jonsson Library, 1988 Nov (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - RWL Awards, 1988 Nov (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - IIS reception talk, 1988 Oct (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - YMCA, 1988 Oct (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Connecticut College, 1988 Oct (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - SU/MIT/CHI/IVY, 1988 Sep (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - SU IVY MIT Conference, 1988 Sep (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - International banquet SU, 1988 Sep (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - C. J. Meyers Memorial, 1988 Sep (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - CUNY "Reagan Among the Corinthians" (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Phone message books (2), 1988 Sep 26-1991 Oct 17 (Box 8)
- Asia/Pacific Research Center, Accession ARCH-1999-014
  - US-Japan Legislators' Committee
    - Japan-US Congressional Seminar (canceled), 1985 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
    - US-Japan Legislators' Committee Meeting, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 3-4)
    - US-Japan Legislators' Committee Meeting, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 5-6)
    - Mid-year Meeting, 1988 Sep (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - US-Japan Legislators' Conference, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - US-Japan Legislators' Conference, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - US-Japan Legislators' Conference, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 10-12)
    - US-Japan Legislators' Committee Meeting, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 13-15)
    - US-Japan Legislators' Committee Meeting, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - US-Japan Legislators' Committee Meeting, Correspondence with Japan, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - US-Japan Legislators' Committee Meeting, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - US-Japan Legislators' Committee Meeting, Correspondence with Japan, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - US-Japan Legislators' Committee Meeting, Correspondence, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - JPERC III (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Japan-US Friendship Commission, High Tech Project, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Asia-Pacific Roundtable
    - Asia-Pacific Roundtable 1995: Asian-US Conference (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Asia-Pacific Roundtable 1995: A-P Leaders Correspondence (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Asia-Pacific Roundtable 1995: A-P Leaders Local Participants (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Asia-Pacific Roundtable 1995: Papers: A-P Roundtable 1995 Meeting (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Asia-Pacific Roundtable 1995: Australia (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Asia-Pacific Roundtable 1995: Bradley (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Asia-Pacific Roundtable 1995: China (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Asia-Pacific Roundtable 1995: Gordon (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Asia-Pacific Roundtable 1995: Habibie (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Asia-Pacific Roundtable 1995: India (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Asia-Pacific Roundtable 1995: Indonesia (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Asia-Pacific Roundtable 1995: Japan (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Asia-Pacific Roundtable 1995: Malaysia (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Asia-Pacific Roundtable 1995: Pakistan (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Asia-Pacific Roundtable 1995: Philippines (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Asia-Pacific Roundtable 1995: Romulo (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Asia-Pacific Roundtable 1995: Singapore (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Asia-Pacific Roundtable 1995: South Korea (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Asia-Pacific Roundtable 1995: Taiwan, ROC (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Asia-Pacific Roundtable 1995: Thailand (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Asia-Pacific Roundtable 1995: Vietnam (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Asia-Pacific Leadership Roundtable (Box 2, Folder 22-25)
    - Asia-Pacific Leaders Roundtable: Agenda/Attendance (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Asia-Pacific Leaders Roundtable: Invitation Letters (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Asia-Pacific Leaders Roundtable: Responses (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Asia-Pacific Leaders Roundtable: Resource People (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Asia-Pacific Leaders Roundtable: Presentations (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Asia-Pacific Leaders Roundtable: Logistics (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Asia-Pacific Leaders Roundtable: Miscellaneous (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Asia-Pacific Leaders Roundtable: Correspondence with Washington (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Asia-Pacific Leaders Roundtable: Golf (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Former Corporate Affiliates
    - Gulf Oil Trading Co., 1985 Nov 1 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Hughes Aircraft, 1990 Jan 8 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - IBM, 1985 Aug 13 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Motorola, Inc., 1989 Jan 3 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Toshiba Corporation, 1986 Oct 1 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - TRW (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - TRW, 1980-84 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Varian Associates, 1978-1985 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Varian Associates, 1990 Feb 6 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Foundations
    - Bradley Foundation (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Japan Economic Foundation (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Kiewit Foundation (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - LUM Foundation (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Meyerson Charitable Trust (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Rohlen Foundation (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Smith Richards Foundation (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Ushiba Memorial Foundation (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Semiconductor
    - Proposal to Electric Companies (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Department of Commerce: Semiconductor/Security (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Japanese Challenge to High Technology, 1982 Dec 2 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Public Policy Issues (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - DSB Recommendations (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Miscellaneous Newspaper Articles (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Wall Street Journal Article: Okimoto, Rowen: "Chips and Defense: What America Needs,", 1987 May 15 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Paper: Okimoto, Rowen and Dahl, 1987 May (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Appendix 4 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - List of Names and Addresses (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Responses (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Funding/Strategy (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Karatsu Visit? (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - Fujitsu/Newco (Fairchild) (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Faculty Seminar (Potential Invites) (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - National Security (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - Forum/ CEPR Project (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - Conference and Draft Paper, 1986 May (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - Paper, 1986 Aug (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - Conference Notes, 1986 Aug 27 (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Conference, 1986 Aug 27 (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - Report, 1986 Dec (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - Invitations, 1987 Jan 23; Invitee lists, 1987 Jan 23 and Feb 20 (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - Invitee list, 1987 Jan 23 (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - Invitations, 1987 Jan 23 (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - RSVP, 1987 Jan 23 (Box 3, Folder 45)
    - Invitee list, 1987 Feb 20 (Box 3, Folder 46)
    - Invitations, 1987 Feb 20 (Box 3, Folder 47)
    - RSVP, 1987 Feb 20 (Box 3, Folder 48)
    - Meeting Materials, 1987 Feb 20 (Box 3, Folder 49)
- Additional Records, Accession ARCH-2003-026
  - InterActions, volume 1-8, 1992-1999 (Box 1)
  - IIS Annual Report, 1994-1995, 1999-2001 (Box 1)
  - Centennial Campaign booklet for The Institute for International Studies (Box 1)
  - VHS tapes from Advisory Council of the IIS First Annual Meeting, 1991 Jan 24-25 (Box 2)
    - Vol. II Closing Remarks by Council Members
    - Vol. III Council Discussion of Global Events
    - Vol. IV Session I: Science and Technology
    - Vol. V Session II: Global Environment
    - Vol. VI Session III: International Security
    - Vol. VII Session IV: International Political Economy
  - VHS tape: The IIS. Stanford as a World University [Exterior label: IIS 1992, but seems to be Vol. I of the 1991 meeting from information in the packet] (Box 2)
  - Packet on Advisory Council of the IIS First Annual Meeting with synopsis and speakers for the above tapes (Box 2)